Guide to the Outburst Archive ca. 1959-1964 MSS.022
Fales Library and Special Collections
Outburst Archive
1959-1964
Fales Library and Special Collections
Outburst (1961-1963)
MSS.022
0.5 Linear Feet
The Outburst Archive is a collection of correspondence and manuscripts received by Tom Raworth while he was publishing Outburst, a poetry magazine produced under the Matrix Press imprint. Noted correspondents include Carol Bergé, Paul Blackburn, William Burroughs, Robert Creeley, Lawrence Ferlinghetti, Allen Ginsberg, Anselm Hollo, LeRoi Jones, Denise Levertov, Michael McClure, Henry Miller, Alain Robbe-Grillet, and Gary Snyder.
Provenance
The collection was acquired in April of 1965.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Biographical and Historical Note
From 1961 to 1963, Tom Raworth edited and published three issues of Outburst, a poetry magazine produced under Raworth's Matrix Press imprint, which also published several small books by authors such as Pete Brown, Edward Dorn, Anselm Hollo, Piero Heliczer, and David Ball. Outburst and the Matrix Press focused on British and American poets, but include other European poets and prose writers as well. Most authors are associated with the Beat poets, the British Poerty Revival, or the Black Mountain school. Six hundred copies of the first issue and 700 copies of the second were produced.
Tom Raworth (b. 1938) is a British poet with over 40 published works of poetry and prose to his credit. Raworth is often associated with the British Poetry Revival of the 1960s and 1970s. His first published book of poetry, Relation Ship, received acclaim when it was released in 1966. He has published poetry steadily since that time and often performs readings of his work. Raworth is also a visual artist producing drawings, paintings, and collages.
Sources:
Raworth, Thomas Moore. "CV." Accessed March 25, 2009. http://www.tomraworth.com/cvweb.html.
Tuma, Keith, ed. Anthology of 20th Century British and Irish Poetry. New York: Oxford University Press, 2001.
Scope and Content Note
The Outburst Archive contains correspondence and manuscripts submitted to Tom Raworth for publication in Outburst or through the Matrix Press. The manuscripts are primarily poetry, but also include prose works.
Arrangement
The Outburst Archive is arranged in alphabetical order by correspondent.
Missing Title
Series I: Correspondence and Manuscripts
Separated Material
There is no information about materials that are associated by provenance to the described materials that have been physically separated or removed.
Poetry, Modern -- 20th century.; Correspondence.; Manuscripts for publication.; Avant-garde (Aesthetics); American literature -- 20th century.; Poets, American -- 20th century.; American fiction -- 20th century.; American poetry -- 20th century.; Small presses -- New York (State) -- New York.; Literature, Experimental |x Periodicals.; Authors, American -- 20th century.; Downtown writers.; New York (N.Y.) -- Intellectual life -- 20th century.; Novelists; Ginsberg, Allen, 1926-1997; Ferlinghetti, Lawrence; Snyder, Gary, 1930-; Enslin, Theodore; Blackburn, Paul; Burroughs, William S., 1914-1997; Robbe-Grillet, Alain, 1922-2008; Raworth, Tom; Miller, Henry; McClure, Michael; Levertov, Denise, 1923-1997; Hollo, Anselm; Bergé, Carol, 1928-; The Outburst Archive; Baraka, Amiri, 1934-2014; Creeley, Robert, 1926-2005
- Series I: Correspondence and Manuscripts
  Scope and Contents note
  Series 1 contains one box of correspondence and manuscripts to Tom Raworth, the editor of Outburst [and the Matrix Press]. Contributing writers include Carol Bergé, Paul Blackburn, William Burroughs, Robert Creeley, Lawrence Ferlinghetti, Allen Ginsberg, Anselm Hollo, LeRoi Jones, Denise Levertov, Michael McClure, Henry Miller, Alain Robbe-Grillet, and Gary Snyder.
  - Archive List, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Barker, Richard, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bergé, Carol, 1961-1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Black, Nigel, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Blackburn, Paul, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bonheim, Helmut, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bremser, Ray, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Brown, Pete, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Burroughs, William, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Capitanchik, Maurice. Collymore, Frank. Combs, Tom, Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Corman, Cid. Corso, Gregory, 1961;1964 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Creeley, Robert, 1961-1963 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Dawson, Fielding, 1961-1963 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Dorn, Edward, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Eigner, Larry, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Enslin, Theodore, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Federman, Raymond. Ferlinghetti, Lawrence, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Finlay, Ian Hamilton, Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Gelber, Jack. Ginsberg, Allen, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Hazard, Geoffrey. Heliczer, Piero, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Holland, Lee, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Hollo, Anselm, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Hollo, Anselm, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Hollo, Anselm, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Hollo, Anselm, Undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Hymes, Dell. Jones, LeRoi, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Keys, John. Kupferberg, Tuli. Levertov, Denise, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Logue, Christopher. McClure, Tom. Maclise, Angus, Undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Malcolm, Tom. Meltzer, David, Undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Micheline, Jack. Miller, Henry, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - The Mini-Cab War, Undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Nichols, Clinton. Olson, Charles. Orlovsky, Peter, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Robbe-Grillet, Alain. Rumaker, Michael. Shayer, Michael, Undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Sillitoe, Alan. Simpson, N.F. Snyder, Gary, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Souster, Raymond. Toynbee, Philip. Tse-Chiang, Chao, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Turnbull, Gael. Wang, David. Webb, Jon Edgar, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Woolf, Douglas, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Misc., undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Weiss, Ruth. Wesker, Arnold. Whalen, Philip, 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Williams, Jonathan. Wolin, Harvey. Zukofsky, Louis, 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 40)